So, I found an interesting sutra, sutra,
sorry, from the Chinese Samyukta Agama.
Number 493.
And it's called sailing upstream.
So, thus have I heard.
On one occasion, the venerable Sariputta
addressed the monks.
If a forest monk is in an empty place in
a forest or at the foot of a tree, he
should undertake this training.
Internally observing and reflecting.
Do I perceive thoughts of sensual desire
within my chitta or not?
If he does not perceive them, but when
encountering sense objects or a sign of
beauty, craving and sensual desire
arise, this opposes being withdrawn.
Yeah. Opposes seclusion, viveka.
Yeah, so I think we can stop there in a
sense. Uh Yeah, so
Yeah, so
if a forest monk goes to an empty place
like the Pali,
in a forest, the foot of a tree,
and as I said before, it's like
>> [clears throat]
>> whereas Pali pretty much
due to the centuries of a
standardization, lost all the nuances.
lost all the nuances.
The Pali would just say, you know, a
monk goes to the forest, foot of a tree,
empty hut, purifies his mind from
unwholesome states. Right, right. And
today purification in a contemporary
sense, purification of unwholesome states
purification of unwholesome states
pretty much it's open to any
interpretation whatsoever. So, whatever
you would have say acquired in a course
of time,
whatever ideas you would have acquired
that the Buddhist practice is all about,
you would interpret purification of
thoughts according to those ideas. So,
if you think purification of thoughts
comes down to
um diligently sitting and watching your
sensations, you would That's how you
would read the sutta. So, there is no
nuances Mhm. in the Pali, especially like when
Mhm. in the Pali, especially like when
it comes to this particular topic
of, you know, the chitta inside of
beauty and stuff.
It It's sort of um
like like fragmented and just
a a a template phrases.
That is I said, it's like with without
like having not discovered say these
Agamas or these extra kind of input from
Agamas, you would be sort of just Well, a lot
you would be sort of just Well, a lot
would be left to like a a wide range of
interpretations. >> Right. Right. Whereby pretty much
>> Right. Right. Whereby pretty much
anything can fit into say the idea of
purification of thoughts. Any any
practice can fit into it. Oh, yeah, I'm
purifying thoughts by doing this, this,
or that.
Cuz again, there is nothing in between
that's explained that you could see that
actually know, like these things
wouldn't fit or these things would fit
more, and so on.
>> Mhm.
And as I said, what's what's um
what's even
more interesting is that all these um
Agamas, as it says even at the end of this one,
as it says even at the end of this one,
were translated from the Pali.
So, they were Pali translations.
And this one in particular
dated from 435 to 443 Common Era.
So, fifth century, basically.
Which means Pali back then
was saying this. Yeah.
It wasn't like
this was written on its own. This is
translated from Pali when those
missionaries came down to like Sri Lanka
and and the
>> Right. Right. started translating the
existing text. Which means in a course
of time,
it was the Pali that got it changed.
They got even more standardized and lost
the nuances.
they were already forms of
standardization. See what I mean? Like fourth, fifth
See what I mean? Like fourth, fifth
century
that's already like what? Six?
Well, 10 centuries after the Buddha
died, it's already standardized. But now
you can see how much even more
standardized I watered down, turned into
template, losing the nuances is today.
So, discovering the Agamas, they were
translations of some period in between
shows you that actually Pali um has
undergone quite a significant
uh um
uh reduction in in the amount of nuances
it contains.
So, it's like
So, it definitely adds to reading the
suttas. For sure. As I said, like this
is, you know, how many people would have
read um um
the uh
you know, a forest monk goes to a an
empty place, a root of a tree, and
purifies his mind of unwholesome things.
It's purifies mind of the five
hindrances. Yeah.
And like not really looked into it
further because there was nothing else
to look into. Then you would naturally
have to resort
to uh um
what any what whatever other kind of
contemporary interpretations
are provided. And usually that kind of
comes through commentaries and the
mainstream views, which is like, "Yes,
purification of hindrances means
meditation technique." There is nothing
else that you can see. Well, you could
if you like start studying the whole
body of Pali, you would see that it
doesn't add up. But most people don't do
that. Most people arrive through one
sutta and then
like like kind of fragmented approach
through sutta here, sutta there, while
the the common binding views behind are
already assumed simply because they're
presented through mainstream Buddhism,
for example. So, you wouldn't
necessarily be questioning that even if
you come across the suttas eventually
that are contradicting those very views.
They do not adding up.
So, in this specific instance, it's like
Yeah, how many times have you read
forest monk goes, purifies his mind,
purifies mind from hindrances, from
unwholesome states.
Uh, and then just as I said, because
it's so generic, so condensed, so
template-like, any practice you were presented with
any practice you were presented with
as a Buddhist practice,
all I need to do is tell you of that's
what the purification of mind means.
Yeah. Counting your breath, watching
sensations, feeling the soles of your
feet. Mantra, repeat Buddha, and you
would have like an average person would
have no reference
as to like
does this add up? Is there more to this?
Cuz you're just, okay, that's that's
what it's connected and
like nothing says that it's wrong, so to
speak. Unless as I said, you start
studying the entire only this and this,
which most people
won't do or, you know, will kind of stop
halfway through, so to speak. Or even if
they do, will not necessarily turn them
into questioning the frequency of
notions of interpretations that they
already started with. So, this is
obviously a a welcome input. Any form of
uh, like Agama in this sense it's like a
direct translation of what Pali used to
say. Even if you can't find the exactly
Even if you can't find the exactly
matching sutta,
you could find the passages that
correspond, and this adds to it. And in
this specific instance, it's like
actually says, I don't think there's any
Pali that says this so clearly, that
when a monk goes into seclusion, goes
into its
uh, uh, forest, uh, root of a tree, he
reflects thus, saying, "Do I perceive
thoughts of sensual desire within my
chitta or not?"
>> [snorts]
>> Yeah, I know.
Internally observing,
internal observations.
>> Yeah. So, and thinking.
Uh
obviously, as I said, cuz it's already a
monk, means you're already say purified
in your external behavior.
You're keeping the precepts and so on.
And then it's like um
you go into a solitary dwelling.
And begin pretty much by the recognition
of me and the animal.
The cheetah. So, the cheetah would have
already been seen sufficiently through
purification of physical behavior.
As we explained so many other times.
So, it's like
So, there is no more
um
confusion as to where to look that I
internal internally observing. You know,
when you're internally observing, you're
looking at the state of the animal.
The overall state of the mind of the
cheetah. I'll stop saying mind. Just
Just cheetah, which is obviously the
mind, but
So, it's like
Are there thoughts or sensuality within
this cheetah? So, is this animal here
and now as I'm sitting with Ron
physically withdrawn, sitting in a in a
in a in a quiet secluded environment,
are there thoughts
that are connected, concerned um
in regard to with sensuality within this
cheetah? Again, not so that I can do this
Again, not so that I can do this
technique, so that I can apply that. No,
no, just a simple reflection Mhm. and
recognition of the internal domain.
Right now, as I'm sitting here alone
with Ron.
Yeah. Just
ask that question in the say in the in
the neutrality of that reflection.
Not for the sake of judgment, not for
the sake of conclusion. Just
are there thoughts right now in this
cheetah that are concerned with
sensuality? Sexuality, sensuality,
any any kind of form of it. And
look for the answer in the state of the
cheetah, not in the state of like, oh,
this I must be like that.
>> that's the thing. So, when uh you know,
I'll be sitting
and doing that same thing
and thinking, okay,
what are there any sensual thoughts in
the cheetah?
And so, you can see, oh, yeah.
The cheetah is inclined I'm I'm not
thinking sensual thoughts, but it is
inclined towards sensuality. It wants to
go in a certain direction.
>> that's the next one. Oh, yeah, so First,
it's like, are there thoughts of
sensuality? If he does not perceive
them, but when encountering sense objects or a
but when encountering sense objects or a
sign of beauty or a thought, craving and
sensual desire arise, this opposes to
being withdrawn. So,
the answer to the first question might
be like, oh, no, I'm not. There are no
thoughts currently besetting the mind.
Okay, that's a neutral recognition.
And that recognition is informed by the
state of cheetah.
They not come as your um
They not come from you as you answering
what you think the answer should be.
That's the difference. Like, that should
be the answer, but you're not looking
for it to come from that place, but you
want it to come from the recognition of
cheetah, which means you're open to any
answer. So, are there thoughts of sensuality
So, are there thoughts of sensuality
connected with the cheetah?
No. At least right now, no.
The next one is, okay, if, however,
Yeah, okay.
>> I were to
think about the sign of beauty. And
that's what it says.
So, in the same way when he reflects on
the perception of beauty. So,
I'm not going in physically exposing my
senses to unsuitable sights, sounds,
smells, tastes, touches.
That's been dealt with through
withdrawal, through taming on that that
level, but now it's like, okay, if I
were to bring up a sign of beauty, a
sign of attractive, a sign of that which
is
incentive, inciting of lust as What's
Pali Sutta say,
Uh
would then the cheetah turn towards it?
Would then the cheetah leap
with excitement towards it?
And then you could already know the
answer. It's like, "Okay, so I'll bring up a
It's like, "Okay, so I'll bring up a
thought again
while keeping a corner of my eye on the
animal, feeling on that mood, on that
generality of like the state that I
feel. Will there be a ripple in it? Will there
Will there be a ripple in it? Will there
be a movement? If so,
cheetah is not free from sensuality.
Again, not so that I can resolve it here
and now this very second. More like just
to see the level of response that comes
from the animal. So, it's literally like
like you have a dog tied down, calmed
down. He's sitting next to you on a
leash. Now you don't know if the dog is calm
Now you don't know if the dog is calm
because recently there hasn't been
anything that's been provoking it
or because it has actually internally
reached the state of Oh, this is a
trained dog.
And it's waiting for your instruction.
Exactly. He won't act on its own its
own. So, you have to, as I said, expose
the triggers to see if the dog will
twitch. And in this sense, those triggers are
And in this sense, those triggers are
not going back to sights, sounds,
smells, tastes, touches of unsuitable
kind, but the triggers are, as the
actual argument says, reflecting on the
perception of beauty.
So, having the thoughts in a controlled
environment. So,
if Yeah. the dog reacts
because it's a controlled environment,
it won't go too far. It will have given
you a um
a sufficient, suitable That's enough of
a feedback. I don't need it to go really
wild running after stuff. And that's
exactly what the paragraph in the sutta
says. So,
So,
if he doesn't perceive the current
thoughts, but when
the cheetah when the animal encounters
the sense object or sign of beauty,
uh craving and sensual desire arises.
and it it's just like a man
forcefully rowing a boat upstream
against the current. So, that is your
current state then. If my cheetah is
calm because I'm keeping it calm, I'm
keeping it withdrawn,
I'm not exposing it to unsuitable sites,
which is what you should do,
but it does react if things were to come
within its range, it's like me rowing a
boat upstream.
So, which means it's going in the right
direction for as long as I'm rowing.
Yeah. But if I stop rowing, the boat
goes back downstream immediately.
That's not enough. [clears throat]
That's not uh sufficient.
And certainly uh as the sutta says like
um he wouldn't be a a monk who
recognizes that would not dare to
declare of himself
um
"Oh, my mind is liberated through this
passion regarding the five cords of
sensual desire." Because he knows that
if circumstances were to change, if I
were to be exposed to unsuitable site,
my mind, basically unless I'm sustaining
the effort of rowing up the stream, my
mind will go back and that's not good
enough. But that's the thing, if people
can a monk can go into the forest and so
on and sit down and
and not be exposed, even avoid sensual
thoughts and so on, and be you know,
secluded in that sense.
>> [clears throat]
>> But
it doesn't it doesn't uh bring these
little triggers up, does it? It doesn't
He hasn't
uh think on the possibility of oh, I
could go towards a sensuality in there.
Well, see, that's like you you find Now,
when you
when we sort of expound on this found in
Agama, you get to see like oh, yeah,
you get to see like oh, yeah,
there are suttas in Pali that say
things such as can an arisen sensual
desire arise in me if I were to attend
to things wrongly?
So, there is that training through the
triggers and stuff, but without the
additional context
such as like what which which this Agama
provides, for example,
again, it can mean anything. But now you
have you have slightly different input,
and now you get to recognize other
things in Pali that actually talk about
the same.
And that would be exactly that. So,
okay, there is no current desire.
That is your work to recognize is there
a current desire? Are there currently
thoughts besetting the chitta?
No. Could there be desire if the thoughts
Could there be desire if the thoughts
were to change?
And you as I said, even without going
into the specifics of the thoughts, you
could already see if there is a trigger,
if the dog twitches, if like oh, is
there something?
And that's already your answer. Yeah.
Yeah. Um but then yes, even if within
that controlled environment, you do um
actually like um bring up
bring up
through that controlled reflection, a
sign of beauty, a sign of attractive,
a preference of yours that always makes
the mind like
you know,
wants to jump towards it. Mhm. And it's
like, oh, okay, so that's what happens.
When I bring this sign of beauty in this
specific specific sign of beauty,
whatever works for you,
>> [snorts]
>> the mind gets agitated. Again, it's not
like I must stop bringing it up.
Like I'll stop bringing it up if the
agitation be uh start becomes too uh
becomes too overwhelming.
But otherwise, I should bring it up
until the dog is not jumping up.
So, I should bring it up through right
attention, through yoniso manasikara. I
should bring it up through right context
to rewrite to re retrain the animal to
not react like this, but to actually
prefer withdrawal from it.
And again, Pali Suttas do say that. When
rightly attended, desire increases.
Sorry, when rightly intended, the arisen
desire decreases and non-arising of
desire basically occurs, so to speak.
So, it's like
Okay, so my work is to be physically
withdrawn,
find a place of seclusion if possible,
or or to the best of my abilities,
and then
start doing the mental work of training
the animal, of bringing up the
triggering things. And by the way, this
is like with centrality, but you realize
in the regard to any ill will, delusion,
fear, anxiety, any hindrance pretty
much. Not to force the animal into submission
Not to force the animal into submission
or something, but to bring it up
and see, "Oh, it jumps up. Why does it
jump up?" Well, it jumps up because it
doesn't see the danger in those
thoughts. So, again,
while bringing up the same signs of
beauty, bring it up within the context of danger
bring it up within the context of danger
of touching it, the context of poison
and stuff. Work your way into that
context and broaden it through
reflection, even like verbal thinking in a way. So,
even like verbal thinking in a way. So,
it's like, "Okay, now I'm bringing it
up, but at the same time, while I'm
showing this to my dog, at the same time
I'm showing it a bigger picture as well,
which is look at the pain implicit in
it." And let it see for itself. It's not
going to immediately see it, but keep it
like that.
And what's the measure of seeing it for
itself? What would be the measure?
That Oh, it's seeing it a bit more for
itself.
What if I go obviously Well, the Sutta
said that the the the dog settles down.
The dog withdraws.
>> say like let's say for example, the dog
is not as excited. Instant trigger, it's
up on its four legs and it's just
waiting to pound. Now, with the right
context behind, kind of
looming behind the immediate signs of
beauty that I have recollected for the
purpose of showing it to the dog to see
its reaction. But I'm also including in
that perception the danger, the peril,
the everything that entails.
everything that entails.
Oh, it twitched, but it didn't get up.
Yeah. Okay. So, let's repeat this. Let's
maintain this. Let's not lose this.
To the point of as as the sūtra goes on,
I mean, we go by the more examples. Um
yeah, to the point of that basically um
when the monk encounters sense objects,
apprehends the signs of beauty, reflects on signs
the signs of beauty, reflects on signs
of beauty, he perceives his citta
inclining away from it.
So, the dog is not just still
in face of provocation,
it actually the animal, not you doing
it, the animal wants nothing to do with
it. Well, turns away from it. It's like,
Well, turns away from it. It's like,
"Oh, I have no interest in this."
And actually, yeah, you can see that
uh on the basis of the dog training that
we are
uh familiar.
Like you give an untrained dog like food from
you give an untrained dog like food from
your hand, and he just grabs it.
Grabs your finger with it.
And then it's like through through
repetition of like, "No."
Not letting it take it like that until
you allow it to.
The point comes, and I remember that
happened with number of the dogs. Like,
as you bring the food in front of them,
they they turn away their head. It's
like, "Oh, I mustn't take it." Mhm.
And they're not So, they can't just
Okay, I mustn't take it, but I just like
like stay with it. No, no, I mustn't
take it. I'll look away. I'll look away
cuz this is danger.
Taking this without permission is
danger. Right, right. So, they look
away, and they continue looking away
until I say, "Okay, go ahead." And then
they take food.
Well, in this case, obviously, there is
no okay, go ahead
in terms of sensuality.
>> Yeah.
But the principle is the is the same.
So, it's like
when the monk encounters sense objects
or apprehends a sign of beauty, if he
perceive if he perceives his cheetah
inclining, flowing, pouring toward being withdrawn
flowing, pouring toward being withdrawn
from the
everything that that sign of beauty
implies.
Then it's just like a bird feather cast
into a fire, it shrivels and curls
unable to unfurl and spread out. So, it
coils away from it, basically.
So, in the same way when the monk
apprehends a sign of beauty, when he
reflects on the sign of beauty, he
instead inclines toward being withdrawn,
flowing and pouring deeply into that
withdrawal, i.e. away from the sign of
beauty. You should know this regarding a monk
You should know this regarding a monk
whose cheetah does not slacken in his
striving sankhara who attains the peace
of dhamma samatha dasa sukha and pure
cheetah with an elevation by turning
away from central perceptions.
Uh and then he can clearly make a
statement that his mind is liberated
through dispassion regarding the five
accords of the central pleasures. Yeah,
that's the measure. That's the measure,
yeah. Not just how you feel. Not how you
feel, not how you
temporarily abide on account of setting
up the right circumstances, which is
necessary, which is supportive, but it's
conditional. So, as as as as we started by
So, as as as as we started by
explaining, it's like, "Oh, but if
circumstances change, where would the
wild animal incline?" Yeah, where would
it pour towards, you know?
Why would it flow hard towards? And
that's the So, even just the possibility
of that central
uh
perception or experience is Do you do
cuz that's what you're doing, you're
showing it's a possibility, yeah.
But and then at the same time you're
showing it the context of danger
regarding that whole possibility. Yeah.
And you wanted to from that place to turn
you wanted to from that place to turn
back already, like, "Oh, yeah, I've seen
the danger now." So, you as soon as that
possibility's there, it the danger is
there for it. The association, if it's
developed sufficiently enough, becomes
inseparable. Like, you have to follow up
by bringing up the which you will have
to do in the beginning.
The possibility, the apprehending of the
sign of beauty, will not be implying the
danger in and of itself. It's something
that you have to keep Hey, hey, I don't
forget about this, though. If you want
that, this is what comes with it.
>> Yeah.
That's the training, that's the
diligence, that's the repetitive work of
not losing that broader picture, as we
often say.
But, you do that long enough,
possibility or a mere apprehension, a
mere uh thinking of a sign of beauty, of
a provocative thought,
the danger is in it. Like, you don't
have to um follow up by adding more
context that's that's now the the
that was previously omitted from it, so
to speak.
So, it's not me rowing upstream anymore,
keeping things going upstream.
It's the genuine
uh preference of the animal. In other
words, I stopped rowing and the boat's
still going in the same direction.
Cuz the animal is now paddling.
>> [laughter] [snorts]
[snorts]
>> Yeah, there's another uh interesting bit
in um
So, back onto the first case, and it's
back onto the first case, and it's
repeated in the second one as well.
It's like, in the same way,
when the monk reflects on the perception
of beauty, craving and sensual desire
arise again,
opposing being withdrawn,
undermining his withdrawal that he's
working. That he worked towards and he's and he's
That he worked towards and he's and he's
maintaining through, as I said,
avoiding unsuitable sights. While this
monk is training in this manner, he
undertakes the development of inferior
striving and does not attain purity. In
other words, his striving is still on
the level of
uh
working with the environment, avoiding
unsuitable sites, and he's not capable
of dwelling in seclusion
and getting the clear references and, as I
getting the clear references and, as I
said, sufficient feedback from the
actual state of cheetah.
That's the
non-inferior. That's the elevated type
of striving. You're not like uh
operating through secondary pointers of
what dog what your dog really wants or
acts towards. You're just reading the
dog's body language without any other
input. You don't need it.
So, that's something that needs to be
worked towards. And again,
here, like you know, this passage
mentioned generally in the Pali, it's
kind of scattered in different passages
and so on that you might, as I said,
um construct the correct image, but
it's never really expressed in this
manner uh as a as a as a whole. clearly,
uh or at least I don't remember a sutta
really off the top of my head.
>> [clears throat]
>> So, because of the inferior striving,
because he's not able
to directly
get the the the live feedback from the
state of his cheetah,
he's swept away once again by craving
and sensual desire, failing to attain
the power of the Dhamma.
Meaning the power of the right context,
the power of um of cuz if you read stuff
directly, live feedback from the
cheetah, again, there is like there's immediate
again, there is like there's immediate
recognition, immediate, no delay uh
response training Mhm. for the animal,
which means that elevates the whole
relationship already, elevates the
cheetah. Protects the withdrawal better, cuz it's
Protects the withdrawal better, cuz it's
not
dependent on circumstances.
So, it's more accurate, so to speak. So,
that's why he because [clears throat] he
doesn't he's not able to do that, he's
swept away when craving and desire
comes. He doesn't attain that effortless
He doesn't attain that effortless
as the Pali would say actually see
attain the power of the Dhamma here the
line corresponds to the
untiring energy arising in me. But in
this case says [clears throat] his
cheetah is still without peace. Lacking
the elevation.
And upon encountering the sign of beauty
craving [clears throat] essential desire
will arise accordingly. Flowing
forcefully and deeply opposing being
withdrawn.
So in other words his practice is still
not astute enough.
astute enough.
It's still not directly
sufficiently recognizing the state of
the animal the state of cheetah without
any kind of inferred secondary
conclusions on account of you know
being physically withdrawn from this
avoiding sight sounds smells tastes
touch that usually results in that and
then if I don't do that results in this.
That's all good and fine when you begin
but it needs to be upgraded to the point
where you don't even need those
secondary reminders.
But literally just internally observing
the state of the mind whether it's
leaning towards oh I want that or not
and already seeing that as a phenomenon
as a thing without needing the extra
interpretation. Of the states of your cheetah.
Of the states of your cheetah.
And that's the then the opposite says
um
for the monk that does
train correctly that is able to now
directly train on the level of whatever
the state cheetah is in.
Um you should know that this monk whose
cheetah does not slacken in his striving
sankhara. So there is no delay. Not slacken means
So there is no delay. Not slacken means
there is no delay. Like his effort is
directly met by the dog. There is no I
got to beat it a few times cuz the dog
is lacking it's not listening it gets
distracted, I need to make it
um more pliable. Now, that has been
done. And now the cheetah doesn't slacken,
And now the cheetah doesn't slacken,
he attains the peace of the dhamma,
samatha, he attains the rest, the
pleasure, sukha,
and the pure eye clean, no delay state
of the animal with elevation. I animal
is now elevated from the things that
corrupt it.
Doesn't want them. Turns away from them,
prefers this.
Having reflected in the presence of the
sign of beauty, so and then you bring up
the sign of beauty and the animal
doesn't want anything to do with it.
In other words, animal understood for
[clears throat] itself everything you've
been telling it up to that point.
Which is a which is what the right
training was, telling the right
perceptions and the right things to that
animal. At the right time.
At the right time, exactly. The dog is
chasing its prey,
you're shouting at it, "Sit! Sit!" Yeah.
And it's like it never happens.
And only people that as I said, people
would do that when they don't know what
are the prerequisites, what are the
necessary steps for the dog to be able
to hear and associate sit with the right
action.
And that's exactly people generally like
your average person who is not familiar
in what the actual early suttas would
say or agamas contribute, but just
follow the generic ideas of Buddhist
practice, meditation, peace.
It would be exactly like that. It would
be like
mind not withdrawn from sensuality, not
withdrawn from hindrances by any means,
only occasionally, only conditionally
when you're on a retreat,
and then doing random stuff that you
yourself don't know what's what it
should result into.
So, in other words, you're saying
commands in a language that you yourself
don't understand, such as
meditating for the pleasure, meditating
through techniques, for the novelty
experiences. You you You quite know what
will come out of it. You just hope
something good will come out of it.
>> Yeah. So, I'm just
>> [clears throat]
>> I'm just reading. I'm just shouting
random words that I don't understand
expecting that the dog that still lives
concerned with its sensual desires will
magically sit down and obey my command.
That's how the divorced
the thing is.
The practices from the actual
application. Yeah, well, you
if you want to train
the dog, you need to see the dog. You
need to find it. So, it's again, it's
mentioned in Pali
that sufficient taming of the dog that
you're supposed to train
is a prerequisite, is a precursor to
the right view, to everything that
comes. Precursor to the right training
of the dog is withdrawing it from
everything unsuitable that's still
keeping it
outwardly wild.
Cuz like your voice is not even a factor
for a wild animal.
Like it there's no like oh, when I hear
this, I must do this or I must stop
doing that. It's literally just another
noise that comes from the external
things >> Noisy environment, yeah. Yeah, I'm just
>> Noisy environment, yeah. Yeah, I'm just
barking everywhere. I'm just barking at
everything, yeah.
The chances of now that animal being
tamed while you're just throwing commands in
while you're just throwing commands in
this untamed
environment.
And you see that again like see that
when somebody
um
when you show somebody how to get their
own dog to sit.
And then they think you speak you're a
whisperer, you speak a magic language
that dogs understand cuz they can't
read, you know? You say it when there's
that eye contact with the dog.
When you get its attention, you know,
now if I say the command, it will
respond. But without getting its eye contact,
But without getting its eye contact,
that's like one of the basic things.
Without getting the eye contact first
I attention is on me
you would see this person then trying to
emulate what they saw you do and just
start saying sit, sit, sit, sit. Yeah.
And dog is like from the start hasn't
paid attention to them. It's like it's
not sitting. Yeah. And then you get him
to pay attention to you even for a
millisecond and in that millisecond you
tell it to sit and it sits.
And externally for somebody who doesn't
understand how training work, it looks
like magic.
>> So yeah, so you you need to just find
the find the animal and the animal needs
to see find find you by yourself.
>> Yeah, yeah. And that's why like it's not
negotiable negotiable the whole
negotiable the whole
the virtue, the precepts. So if you
can't do the eight precepts, your
training then of that striving sankhara
or or or or rowing your boat up the
stream has to be concerned with okay,
increasing my capacity to be able to
keep the eight precepts.
To be celibate, to be withdrawn from
sensuality in those uh as I said,
outwardly coarse manners. If I'm failing
that, uh there is no subtle recognition
of the state of my German Shepherd that
I'm training. No, I says. Yeah.
Conditionally I can maybe containing
every now and then, but generally I'm
very much under its own rule, not other
way around.
And there's a danger there. It's like
you think you're practicing, but
if you're not seeing this feedback that
your mind is not turning away from these
possibilities of sensuality, then if the
thing is your prac your striving is
going to end sometime. Yeah. You can get
sick and your little circumstantial
spiritual life
Sooner or later, Done.
>> whatever circumstantially would have
built up, Yeah. if it stays
circumstantial, will have to go away.
>> And the mind's going to go back to what
it
>> which means then flow force forcefully
in the direction it wants to go. Yeah.
Cuz people by not recognizing that it's
a big danger, that's how people remain
very much within the scope of that
danger by thinking oh, it's not a
problem. Yeah, cuz I feel great now.
Yeah. And it it's not a problem feeling great
And it it's not a problem feeling great
now. But you need to recognize that
or reflect on whether you are feeling
great now
whether that comes
on account of you have circumstantially
protected yourself through the right
environment and this and that and having
nothing trigger you
or having every
ready psychological kind of
rationalizations ready whenever triggers
come up to like quickly
okay but that's that that's this and
dismiss it and not have the the state of
the agitated animal that you have to
endure. Or you recognize that your peace
comes from all of not doing any of that.
So it's like I've done the right
circumstances provided and stuff but
then I've also endured the agitation of
the animal without acting out rightly
learn to read its signs directly
having not acted out in any ways brought
up the triggers so to see whether the
animal will stay calm if he doesn't stay
calm I repeat you know the brooding of
the context of the danger and stuff and
now it's calm and now it's acting it's
like oh now I can actually relax. Like
that the two types of thoughts with the
says. After a while
he would you know the shepherd can go to
sleep basically and the cows would still
be there they would not
wander back into the unsuitable pastures
like how they used to do.
And it's like okay that peace is fine
and you can make your claim and your
attainments and stuff.
But if it's
circumstantial or if you're not sure
means it's circumstantial basically.
Which means when conditions change and
you end up in a hospital or something
where you cannot micromanage
the input that comes through your senses
and stuff or or or resort to your
meditation technique in a perfect
silence or in a in a in artificial
environment of a meditation retreat
and it's like You can't manage. Well the
animal would just just be as wild as it
always was. You want the thing to be
free and to be doing the right things
Yeah. by itself. By itself. That's the
goal. You want it to be liberated from
You want it to be liberated from
Exactly. That's why he knows it's
liberated.
It is that you know
when it a
that which used to or that which
makes you angry
you get angry from and then you
encounter things that are
uh
invocative of anger Yeah. provocative
sorry of anger and the mind
you don't have to tell the mind anything
and it just
turns away from that like experience and
just >> you might you might even surprise you in
>> you might you might even surprise you in
that sense. If you've been training
right Right. Right. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
You don't necessarily cuz obviously
you're not seeking out the coarse
triggers for sensuality or you will
operating on the level of thoughts uh
>> [clears throat]
>> apprehensions of the sign of beauty or
the ugly or the provocative things one
way or the other.
And you're doing that's your work.
That's your concern. And then
something does enter through your eyes,
through [clears throat] your nose,
through your so on that used to and then
you you kind of you're braced. You're
waiting for the
raging animal because this is my trigger
for anger
and then you look the animal is actually
laying down and then you realize oh it's
calm. The training works.
I didn't do this. It chose this. I was
actually ready for it to start barking.
It didn't. That's why those examples
[clears throat] in the suttas um monks
suddenly faced a prospect of death. That's when
faced a prospect of death. That's when
they realized that their work was done.
Not before that. Their work was actually
done. They were arahants before that.
But they just were not necessarily
certain about it
cuz nothing provoked the mind to the
extent of them to see that oh even death
the mind is calm.
Didn't move. Therefore, it's liberated.
Therefore, I know now that it's
liberated cuz this has proven it to me.
So, when they are when that monk almost
I don't know stumbled upon these people
about to set somebody on fire and then
they want to kill him.
And his mind became liberated there and
then. And then you think, "Oh, he was so
lucky." It's like, "Well, no. He already
did the work." There and then he
recognized for himself that the animal
was calm because the extreme scenario
that he could not have even imagined in
its its kind of extremeness,
he was ready for the mind to start
kicking, screaming, defending itself, or
being affected by fear.
And then he looked back and the mind was
completely unmoved. So, it came as a
surprise to him, but not as a shock
because he knows why that was. He just
wasn't didn't expect it that it's going
to be there and then in that instance.
Or like the path of Tetha Tetha got
there, it's all about
the the sudden recognition of the mind
mind being liberated or calm after like,
I don't know, doing
relentless for who knows how long
reflection on the right things uh
uh
like I can't remember the story like bleeding
I can't remember the story like bleeding
out of the feet cuz he was just
reflecting on stuff so long
that he was walking back and forth
forgot for how long and his feet started
to split and bleed. He's like, "Okay,
I'll stop this too much for now. You
know, wash my feet." And as the mud came
off the feet,
he realized, "Oh, the mind was calm."
Not because I was washing the feet in
the river, but because all the prior
work of taming.
I was so concerned with uh providing the
right context, maintaining the right
danger. He didn't notice the dog is
actually not not moving anyway. He he
stopped. He was already calm.
>> No more training needed. No more
training needed.
>> yes.
Yeah, I think it was the monk who was
walking up and down then he got up to
walk and then he fell over.
>> Fell he couldn't. [snorts] Yeah, he was
just so tired he just couldn't walk.
>> at that point Then "Oh." But see, again,
like you read just that without the context
well, an uninstructed person not
familiar with the early suttas
uh would or quite often ends up
concluding is okay, so if I just do relentlessly
is okay, so if I just do relentlessly
determined walking up and down.
So, the act of walking is what purified
me. Yeah. Yeah. It's like, no, it's the
act of purifying your mind according to
these standards, according to these
descriptions. Um
Um
while walking. Mhm.
But yeah, if you just read what
the little bit of condensed Pali says,
"Oh yeah, just walk back and forth. I'll
just walk back and forth."
What do I do in the meantime? Well, I
don't know any of these nuances.
This is too abstract. I'll watch the
soles of my feet.
I'll feel the sensations of the ground.
I'll feel earth-ed or connected and
stuff. Just anything random I can put
into it to give it more meaning.
But it was already misconstrued from the
start. It's not about the walking. Yeah.
It's not about the walking. Yeah.
>> It's not about sitting. It's not even
about the breathing in Anapanasati. It's
about the implicit peripheral training
that you do through your breath.
Through the recognition of the body
breathing and so on.
Yeah, after the meal, he goes to the
forest to an empty hut. And then he and then he
to an empty hut. And then he and then he
trains his
>> Which is just a condensed way of
describing a sustained of a lifestyle
that sustained away from coarse
sensuality, coarse engagement with
uh duties, distractions, irritations,
five senses, five sense objects, and so
on. That's what it means. Doesn't mean
literally I must find the root of a tree
where I will plant myself sitting like
this or like that and then do this
mechanical Yeah. uh uh method of just
adhering to these steps and magical
result will occur.
No, he just means
Oh, this is how you live now. It's not a
occasional exposure to the right
environment, occasional exposure to the
which is good for somebody who is
completely immersed in the five cords of
sensuality. But it's nowhere near enough to begin to
But it's nowhere near enough to begin to
see the animal, the state it is for what
it is accurately without needing the
secondary, as I said, rationalizations
and uh contemplations and reflections.